<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="app_name">Syllabus</string>


    <!-- TODO: Remove or change this placeholder text -->
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>
    <string name="open">open</string>
    <string name="close">close</string>
    <string name="aboutInfo">This app will provide you with information regarding syllabus of BTech ,Result which is provided by IKGPTU (I.K. Gujral Punjab Technical University ). This syllabus is taken from official website of PTU . Regarding any mistake or error in the syllabus of any branch or any semester feel free to inform me via given email(bhatiahemant128@gmail.com) or whatsapp me on  +918950550801 .</string>
    <string name="aboutinfo2">We will try to give you many more features regarding PTU in our upcoming updates .</string>

    <string name="sendData">Here is all new PTU Syllabus app ,with many more features like ptu previous year
        question paper , PTU Result , PTU Website and many more ,\nso download it now </string>

    <string name="sem1_sub1">Part A (Electrical Engineering)\n\n1. Direct Current (DC) Circuits:\n\nCircuit elements and connected terminology, Kirchhoff\'s Laws-Statement and Illustrations, Method of solving circuits by Kirchoff\'s law, Star-Delta Conversion, Computation of resistance at constant temperature, resistance at different temperatures, Ohm\'s Law- Statement, Illustration and Limitation, Units- Work, Power and Energy (Electrical, Thermal and Mechanical). DC Transients for RL and RC series circuits.\n\n2. Alternating Current (AC) Fundamentals:\nGeneration of alternating electromotive force EMF, Concept of 3-phase EMF Generation, Peak, Root Mean Square and Average value of alternating current, Phasor representation of alternating quantities, Analysis of AC Circuit Representation of Alternating Quantities in Rectangular and polar forms.Introduction of Resistive, Inductive and Capacitive circuits and their series and parallel combinations.Concept of resonance in series and parallel circuits, Analysis of balanced 03 phase system with star-delta connections.\n\n3. Magnetic Circuits and Transformer:\n\nComparison between magnetic and electric circuits, Magnetic effects of electric current, Current carrying conductor in magnetic field, Law of Electromagnetic Induction and its law, Self Inductance, Mutual Inductance, Coupling Coefficient between two magnetically coupled circuits. Single Phase Transformer: Construction, Working principle, Efficiency, Voltage regulation and applications.\n\n4. Rotating Electrical Machines:\n\nD.C. machines (motors and generators), Three phase Induction motor, Synchronous machines (motors and generators): construction, working principle, classification and applications.\n\nPart B (Electronics Engineering)\n\n5. Transducers:\n\nIntroduction, working and application of LVDT, Strain Gauge and Thermistor. Introduction and application of Digital Multimeter.\n\n6. Semiconductor Devices:\n\nPrinciple of operation characteristic and application of PN Junction Diode, Rectifiers, Zener Diode, Principle of operation characteristic and application of Bipolar Junction Transistor, Principle of operation and characteristic Field Effect Transistor, Regulated Power Supply.\n\n7. Digital Electronics:\n\nBinary, Octal and Hexadecimal number System and its arithmetic operations, Logic gates, Introduction of R-S, J-K, D and T Flip Flops and its truth tables.</string>
    <string name="sem1_sub2">PART A (Reading)\n\nThe prescribed reading textbook for students will beS. P. Dhanavel English and Communication Skills for Students of Science and Engineering (with audio CD), Orient Blackswan. They will go through the reading texts themselves with the help of a dictionary or word power as given at the end. As they progress from one reading to another they should learn to read fast with greater degree of understanding of both concrete and abstract topics. While taking up the textbook lessons in the classroom, the teacher shall ensure that students can do the following:\n\ni. Identify the significant points and conclusions as given in the text.\n\nii. Handle large texts (even outside the prescribed book) with overall comprehension of the links between arguments and the finer distinction between stated and implied meanings.\n\niii. Generally read the stance or the point of view of the writer and present it in the form of a summary iv. Use the vocabulary learnt in the lessons (especially given in ,, word power") productively in various writing tasks as suggested at the end of each lesson.\n\nv. Profitably use the grammatical items as discussed at the end of each lesson while producing language for communication.\n\nBesides the textbook, the teacher must insist that students extend their reading by taking up additional texts of their own choice.\n\nPART B (Writing)\n\nIn addition to the various exercises given at the end of each lesson of Dhanavel's book, the teacher shall use Anne Laws Writing Skills, Orient Blackswan to teach the language and conventions of writing. The students must learn the language that expresses various cognitive functions that are frequently used in writing. With the help of the teacher who will give them adequate practice, the students should be able to:\n\ni.Convey information 8A GBREFETE 8F abstract tepies with clarity and precision.\n\nii.Write about objects or events with appropriate detail in both descriptive and narrative form.\n\niii.Explain ideas and build up arguments with adequate support in a convincing manner.\n\niv.Use language with some degree of flexibility in conseration to the reader.\n\nv.Produce effectively such forms of professional writing as business letter, emails, notes, memos, reports summaries etc.\n\nWhile teaching, the teacher must inculcate in students the habit of revising their writing. The teacher can also use and recommend the relevant sections of the following books for develoning writing skills in students</string>
    <string name="sem1_sub3">PART A\n\n1. Course Introduction - Need, Basic Guidelines, Content and Process for Value Education:\n\nUnderstanding the need, basic guidelines, content and process for Value Education Self Exploration-what is it?- its content and process; ,Natural Acceptance"\n\nand Experiential Validation as the mechanism for self exploration. Continuous Happiness and Prosperity-A look at basic Human Aspirations Right understanding, Relationship and Physical Facilities- the basic requirements for fulfillment of aspirations of every human being with their correct priority.Understanding Happiness and Prosperity correctly- A critical appraisal of the current scenario.Method to fulfill the above human aspirations: understanding and living in harmony at various levels.\n\n2. Understanding Harmony in the Human Being - Harmony in Myself!:\n\nUnderstanding human being as a co-existence of the sentient," and the material, Body" Understanding the needs of Self (,,!") and „Body" - Sukh and Suvidha Understanding the Body as an instrument of 1" (1 being the doer, seer and enjoyer) Understanding the characteristics and activities of I" and harmony in ,"\n\nUnderstanding the harmony of I with the Body: Sanyam and Swasthya; correct appraisal of Physical needs, meaning of Prosperity in detail Programs to ensure Sanyam and Swasthya.\n\n3. Understanding Harmony in the Family and Society Harmony in Human Human Relationship:\n\nUnderstanding harmony in unit of human interaction Understanding values in human-human relationship, meaning of Nyaya and program for its fulfillment to ensure Ubhay-tripti; Trust (Vishwas) and Respect (Samman) as the foundational values of relationship Understanding the meaning of Vishwas; Difference between intention and competence Understanding the meaning of Samman, Difference between respect and differentiation; the other salient values in relationship Understanding the harmony in the society (society being an extension of family): Samadhan, Samridhi, Abhay, Sah-astitva as comprehensive Human Goals. Visualizing a universal harmonious order in society- Undivided Society (Akhand Samaj), Universal Order (Sarvabhaum Vyavastha )- from family to world family! Family- the basic\n\nPART B\n\n4. Understanding Harmony in the Nature and Existence - Whole existence as Co-existence:\n\nUnderstanding the harmony in the Nature Interconnectedness and mutual fulfillment among the four orders of nature- recyclability and self-regulation in nature Understanding Existence as Co-existence (Sah-astitva) of mutually interacting units in all-pervasive space Holistic perception of harmony at all levels of existence.\n\n5. Implications of the above Holistic Understanding of Harmony on Professional Ethics:\n\nHarmony on Professional Ethics:\n\nNatural acceptance of human values Definitiveness of Ethical Human Conduct Basis for Humanistic Education, Humanistic Constitution and Humanistic Universal Order.\n\nCompetence in professional ethics:\n\nAbility to utilize the professional competence for augmenting universal human order.\n\no Ability to identify the scope and characteristics of people-friendly and eco-friendly production systems.\n\no Ability to identify and develop appropriate technologies and management patterns for above production systems.\n\nCase studies of typical holistic technologies, management models and production systems Strategy for transition from the present state to Universal Human Order:\n\no At the level of individual: as socially and ecologically responsible engineers, technologists and managers o At the level of society: as mutually enriching instituations and organizations</string>
    <string name="sem1_sub4">PART A\n\n1. Differential Calculus:\n\nCurve tracing: Tracing of Standard Cartesian; Parametric and Polar curves; Curvature of Cartesian, Parametric and Polar curves.\n\n2. Integral Calculus:\n\nRectification of standard curves; Areas bounded by standard curves; Volumes and surfaces of revolution of curves; Applications of integral calculus to find centre of gravity and moment of inertia.\n\n3. Partial Derivatives:\n\nFunction of two or more variables; Partial differentiation; Homogeneous functions and Euler\'s theorem; Composite functions; Total derivative; Derivative of an implicit function; Change of variable; Jacobians.\n\n4. Applications of Partial Differentiation:\n\nTangent and normal to a surface; Taylor"s and Maclaurin series for a function of two variables; Errors and approximations; Maxima and minima function of several variables; Lagrange"s method of undetermined multipliers.\n\nPART B\n\n5. Multiple Integrals:\n\nA brief introduction of cylinder, cone and standard conicoids. Double and triple integral and their evaluation, change of order of integration, change of variable, Application of double and triple integration to find areas and volumes.\n\n6. Vector Calculus:\n\nScalar and vector fields, differentiation of vectors, velocity and acceleration. Vector differential operators: Del, Gradient, Divergence and Curl, their physical interpretations. Formulae involving Del applied to point functions and their products. Line, surface and volume integrals.\n\n7. Application of Vector Calculus:\n\nFlux, Solenoidal and Irrotational vectors. Gauss Divergence theorem. Green\'s theorem in plane, Stoke\'s theorem (without proofs) and their applications.</string>
    <string name="sem1_sub5"> PART A\n\n1. EM waves and Dielectrics:\n\nPhysical significance of Gradient, Divergence and Curl, Relationship between Electric Field and Potential, Dielectric polarization, displacement Current, Types of polarization, Maxwell\'s Equations, Equation of EM waves in free space, velocity of EM waves, Poynting vector, Electromagnetic Spectrum (Basic ideas of different region).\n\n2. Magnetic Materials and Superconductivity:\n\nBasic ideas of Dia, Para, Ferro and Ferri, Ferrites, Magnetic Anisotropy, Magnetostriction its applications in production of Ultrasonic waves, Superconductivity, Superconductors as ideal diamagnetic materials, Signatures of Superconducting state, Meissner Effect, Type I and Type Ii superconductors, London Equations, Introduction to BCS theory.\n\n3. Elements of crystallography:\n\nUnit cell, Basis, Space lattice, Crystal Systems, Miller Indices of Planes and Directions in cubic system, Continuous and Characteristic X-Rays, X-Ray Diffraction and Bragg\'s law in Crystals, Bragg\'s spectrometer, X-ray radiography.\n\n4.  Lasers:\n\nSpontaneous and Stimulated emissions, Einstein\'s Coefficients, Population Inversion, Pumping Mechanisms, Components of a laser System, Three and four level laser systems; Ruby, He-Ne, C02 and semiconductor Lasers, Introduction to Holography.\n\nPART B\n\n5. Fibre Optics:\n\nIntroduction, Acceptance Angle, Numerical Aperture, Normalized frequency, Modes of propagation, material dispersion and pulse broadening in optical fibres, fibre connectors, splices and couplers, applications of optical fibres.\n\n6. Special Theory of Relativity:\n\nConcept of Ether, Michelson Morley Experiment, Einstein\'s postulates, Lorentz transformation equations; length, time and simultaneity in relativity, addition of velocity, variation of mass with velocity, Mass-Energy and Energy-momentum relations.\n\n7. Quantum Theory:\n\nNeed and origin of quantum concept, Wave-particle duality, Matter waves, Group and Phase velocities, Uncertainty Principle, Significance and normalization of wave function, Schrodinger wave equation: time independent and dependent, Eigen functions and Eigen values, particle in a box.\n\n8. Nanophysics:\n\nNanoscale, surface to volume ratio, electron confinement, nanoparticles (1D, 2D, 3D), Nanomaterials, Unusual properties of nanomaterials, synthesis of nanomaterials- ball milling and sol-gel techniques, Carbon nanotubes (synthesis and properties),applications of nanomaterials .</string>

    <string name="sem1_prac1">1. To verify Ohm\'s Law and its limitations.\n\n2. To verify Kirchhoff\'s Laws.\n\n3. To measure the resistance and inductance of a coil by ammeter-voltmeter method.\n\n4. To find voltage-current relationship in a R-L series circuit and to determine the power factor of the circuit.\n\n5. To verify the voltage and current relations in star and delta connected systems.\n\n6. To measure power and power factor in a single-phase AC circuit.\n\n7. To verify series and parallel resonance in AC circuits.\n\n8. To observe the B-H loop of ferromagnetic core material on CRO.\n\n9. To use a bridge rectifier for full-wave rectification of AC supply and to determine the relationship between RMS and average values of the rectified voltage.\n\n10. To measure the minimum operating voltage, current drawn, power consumed, and the power factor of a fluorescent tube light.\n\n11. To verify the working of a).\n\nThermocouple b). Strain Gauge c). LVDT.\n\n12. To verify the rating of compact fluorescent lamp (CFL).\n\n13. To obtain the characteristics of a P-N junction diode.\n\n14. To verify the truth table of logic gates.\n\n15. To connect the following ,measuring instruments to measure current, voltage and power in AC/DC circuits:\n\ni. Moving Coil Instruments ii. Moving Iron Instruments ii. Dynamometer Instruments iv. Multimeter-both Digital and Analog Type\n\n16. To obtain the characteristics of a transistor under common base (CB) and common emitter (CE) configuration.\n\n17. To perform open- and short circuit tests on a single phase transformer and calculate its efficiency\n\n18. To start and reverse the direction of rotation of a\n\ni. DC motor ii. Induction motor\n\nNote: Each student is required to perform at least ten experiments\n\n</string>
    <string name="sem1_prac2">Lab Exercises\n\nListening and Speaking\n\nThe audio CD accompanying S.P. Dhanavel book shall be played in the lab to get the students familiar with the standard spoken English. The students must develop a high degree of understanding of spoken material as used in academic and professional environment. The teacher shall help them in the following:\n\na) With the accent of the speaker if it is unfamiliar to them.\n\nb) The Standard English sounds and pronunciation of words.\n\nc) With the topical vocabulary and the idiomatic expressions which are generally part of colloquial speech.\n\nd) With the implied relationships in larger texts, if they are not stated explicitly.\n\nIn addition to the above, extended listening sessions shall be arranged to promote speaking activities among students. For this purpose, a set of twin books K. Sadanand and S. Punitha Spoken English Part I and II, A Foundation Course (with audio CD), Orient Blackswan, is prescribed for use.\n\nThe teachers shall play the CDs selectively in the lab and involve the students in the practice work based on them. While taking up lessons, the teacher must promote the use of dictionaries for correct pronunciation and give ample practice on word stress and weak forms. The students are also supposed to supplement their listening practice by regularly viewing news/knowledge channels on the TV or lecture videos on the internet. At the end of a session, a good speaker must:\n\na)Be able to produce long turns without much hesitation in an accent that is understood all around.\n\nb)Have ready access to a large lexis and conventional expressions to speak fluently on a variety of topics.\n\nc)Have a knack for structured conversation or talk to make his transitions clear and natural to his listeners.\n\nThe teacher may use following different classroom techniques to give practice and monitor the progress of the students:\n\nrole play question answer discussion presentation of papers seminars</string>
    <string name="sem1_prac3">1. To study the magnetic field of a circular coil carrying current.\n\n2. To find out polarizability of a dielectric substance.\n\n3. To study the laser beam characteristics like; wave length using diffraction grating aperture and divergence.\n\n4. To study laser interference using Michelson\'s Interferometer.\n\n5. Study of diffraction using laser beam and thus to determine the grating element.\n\n6. To determine numerical aperture of an optical fibre.\n\n7. To determine attenuation and propagation losses in optical fibres.\n\n8. To find out the frequency of AC mains using electric-vibrator.\n\n9. To find the refractive index of a material using spectrometer.\n\n10. To find the refractive index of a liquid.\n\n11. To study B-H curve using CRO.\n\n12. To find the velocity of ultrasound in liquid.\n\n13. To determine the grain size of a material using optical microscope.\n\nNote: Each student is required to perform at least ten experiments</string>


    <string name="sem2_sub1">PART A\n\n1. Spectroscopy and its Applications:\n\nAn introduction UV/Visible Spectroscopy: Selection rules; Line widths and intensity of spectral lines; Principle and instrumentation; Electronic Transitions; Chromophores and auxochromes; Factors affecting AMax and intensity of spectral lines; Franck-Condon principle; Applications. IR Spectroscopy: Principle and instrumentation; Vibrational frequency: Fundamental modes of vibrations and types; Harmonics; Factors affecting vibrational frequency: Applications. NMR Spectroscopy: Principle and instrumentation; Chemical shift; Spin-Spin Splitting; High resolution NMR spectrum (PMR only).\n\n2. Photochemistry:\n\nIntroduction; Photophysical and photochemical processes; Light sources in photochemistry; Beer-Lambert Law; Laws of Photochemistry, Quantum yield (primary and overall); Primary and secondary photochemical reactions; Jablonski diagram; Semiconductor photochemistry, Photovoltaic cells, Introduction to optical sensors, Introduction to supra-molecular photochemistry.\n\n3. Water and its Treatment:\n\nBoiler feed water: Specification, Scales and sludge fermentation; Priming and foaming; Different methods of the water purification and softening;Desalination of water; Water for domestic use: Specification; Disinfection of water.\n\n4. Green Chemistry and its Applications:\n\nIntroductory overview - Definition and concepts of Green chemistry, Emergence of Green chemistry; Twelve principles of Green Chemistry with emphasis on the use of alternative feedstock (bio-fuels); Use of innocuous reagents in natural processes; Alternative solvents, Design of the safer chemicals; Designing alternative reaction methodology. Microwave and ultrasonic radiation in Green synthesis - Minimizing energy consumption.\n\nPART B\n\n5. Corrosion and its Prevention:\n\nIntroduction; Different types of corrosion - Wet and Dry corrosion; Different types of surface films; Mechanisms of wet corrosion; Galvanic corrosion; Galvanic Series; Concentration cell corrosion and differential aeration corrosion; Soil and microbial corrosions; waterline, stress corrosion; Various methods of corrosion control.\n\n6. Polymers and Reinforced Composites:\n\nIntroduction; Functionality; Types of polymerization; Specific features of polymers; Structures - regularity and irregularity; Tacticity of polymers; Average molecular weights and size; Determination of molecular weight by number average method; Effect of molecular weight on the properties of polymers; Introduction to polymer reinforced composite.\n\n7. Nanochemistry:\n\nIntroduction; Materials self-assembled, Molecular vs. materials self-assembly; Self-assembling materials. Two dimensional assemblies.Mesoscale self assembly; Coercing colloids; Nanocrystals; Supramolecular structures; Nanoscale materials; Future perspectives.\n\n8. Petrochemicals:\n\nIntroduction; First, second and third generation petrochemicals; Primary Raw Materials for Petrochemicals.Natural gas: Natural gas treatment processes; Natural gas liquids; Properties of natural gas; Crude oil: Composition of crude oil- Hydrocarbon compounds; Non-hydrocarbon compounds; Metallic Compounds, Crude oil classification; Physical separation processes; Conversion processes; Production of ethylene and proplene</string>
    <string name="sem2_sub2">PART A\n\n1. Introduction:\n\nEngineering Drawing/Engineering Graphics/Technical Drawing - a Visual Science. Types of Engineering Drawing, Introduction to drawing equipment and use of instruments. Symbols and conventions in drawing Practice. Types of lines and their use, BIS codes for lines, Technical lettering as per BIS codes, Introduction to Dimensioning, Concepts of scale in drawing, Types of scales. Basic Definition of geometrical objects: Points, lines, planes and solids.\n\n2. Theory of Projections:Relevance of projection, Type of projections, Perspective, Orthographic, Axonometric and their basic principles, System of orthographic projection:\n\nin reference to quadrants and octants, illustration through simple problems of projection.\n\n3. Projection of Points:\n\nProjection of points in quadrants and octants.\nProjection of point on Auxiliary planes.\n\n4. Projection of Lines:\n\nParallel to both H P and V P, Parallel to one and inclined to other, and inclined to both, contained in profile plane. True length and angle orientation of straight line: rotation method and auxiliary plane method. Distance between two non intersecting lines, and trace of line.\n\n5. Projection of Planes:\n\nDifference between plane and lamina. Projection of lamina Parallel to one and perpendicular to other Perpendicular to one and inclined to other, Inclined to both reference planes, and Lamina oblique to three reference planes. Application of auxiliary planes, and trace of planes.\n\n6. Projection of Solids:\n\nDefinition of solids, types of solids, and elements of solids. Projection of solids in first or third quadrant, with axis parallel to one and perpendicular to other, axis parallel to one inclined to other, axis inclined to both the principle plane, axis perpendicular to profile plane and parallel to both H P and VP. Visible and invisible details in the projection. Use rotation and auxiliary plane method to draw the projections.\n\nPART B\n\n7. Section of Solids:\n\nDefinition of Sectioning and its purpose. Procedure of Sectioning, Types of sectional planes. Illustration through examples.\n\n8. Intersection of Surfaces/Solids:\n\nPurpose of intersection of surfaces, Intersection between the two cylinder, two prisms, prism and pyramid, pyramid and pyramid, cylinder and prism, cone and cylinder, sphere and cylinder etc., use of cutting plane and line method.\n\n9. Development of Surface:\n\nPurpose of development, Parallel line, radial line and triangulation method. Development of prism, cylinder CORE and pyramid surface for both right angled and oblique solids, and development of surface of sphere.\n\n10. Isometric Projection:\n\nClassification of pictorial views, Basic Principle of Isometric projection, Difference between isometric projection and isometric drawing. Isometric projection of solids such as cube, prism, pyramid and cylinder, and assignments on isometric projection of simple machine parts.\n\n11. Orthographic Projection:\n\nReview of principle of Orthographic Projection, Sketch/drawing of blocks, and of simple machine</string>
    <string name="sem2_sub3">Part A\n\n1. Introduction:\n\nDefinition and scope and importance of multidisciplinary nature of environment. Need for public awareness.\n\n2. Natural Resources:\n\nNatural Resources and associated problems, use and over exploitation, case studies of forest resources and water resources.\n\n3. Ecosystems:\n\nConcept of Ecosystem, Structure, interrelationship, producers, consumers and decomposers, ecological pyramids-biodiversity and importance. Hot spots of biodiversity.\n\n4. Environmental Pollution:\n\nDefinition, Causes, effects and control measures of air pollution, Water pollution, Soil pollution, Marine pollution, Noise pollution, Thermal pollution, Nuclear hazards. Solid waste Management: Causes, effects and control measure of urban and industrial wastes.\nRole of an individual in prevention of pollution.\nPollution case studies. Disaster Management: Floods, earthquake, cyclone and landslides.\n\nPART B\n\n5. Social Issues and the Environment From Unsustainable to Sustainable development, Urban problems related to energy, Water conservation, rain water harvesting, watershed management.\nResettlement and rehabilitation of people; its problems and concerns. Case studies. Environmental ethics:\nIssues and possible solutions. Climate change, global warming, acid rain, ozone layer depletion, nuclear accidents and holocaust. Case studies. Wasteland reclamation. Consumerism and waste products.\nEnvironment Protection Act. Air (Prevention And Control of Pollution) Act. Water (Prevention and control of pollution) Act. Wildlife Protection Act, Forest Conservation Act, Issues involved in enforcement of environmental legislation Public awareness.\n\n6. Human Population and the Environment, Population growth, variation among nations. Population explosion- Family Welfare Programme. Environment and human health, Human Rights, Value Education, HIV/ AIDS. Women and child Welfare. Role of Information Technology in Environment and human health. Case studies.</string>
    <string name="sem2_sub4">PART-A\n\n1. Basic Concepts of Thermodynamics:\n\nDefinition of thermodynamic: Need to study thermodynamics; Application areas of thermodynamic; Difference between Microscopic (or, Statistical) thermodynamics and Macroscopic(or, Classical) thermodynamics, Brief concept of continuum; Thermodynamic System: definition, types (Open, Closed and Isolated) and their examples; Thermodynamic System Boundary: definition, types and their examples; Surroundings; Control(fixed) mass and Control Volume concept and their example, Thermodynamic State; Thermodynamic Property:definition, types citing their examples; condition for any quantity to be a property: State postulate; Thermodynamic equilibrium (which includes Thermal, Mechanical and Chemical equilibrium etc.) and its criterion; Thermodynamic path; Thermodynamic process: definition, concepts of reversible process, quasistatic (or, quasi-equilibrium) process, irreversible process, conditions for reversibility and how these are met with, non-flow processes and flow processes, method of representation of reversible and irreversible process on property diagrams; Cyclic process; Thermodynamic Cycle: definition and its concept; Energy and its forms (microscopic and macroscopic); Physical insight to internal energy, Energy transfer across system boundary i.e. transient energies (heat and work); Difference between heat and work; Sign conventions for heat and work interactions; heat and work as path functions; Equality of Temperature and Zeroth law of Thermodynamics.\n\n2. First Law of Thermodynamics and its applications:\n\nDefinition, essence and corollaries or consequences of first law of Thermodynamics; Expressions for First law of Thermodynamics for a control mass undergoing a Cycle and for process (i.e., a change in state of a control mass); Concept of Enthalpy and total energy and differentiation between the two - a thermodynamic property; Compressible and incompressible substances, Specific heats, Difference between Internal Energy and Enthalpy of compressible and incompressible substances; Representation of first law of thermodynamics as rate equation; Analysis of non-flow/ flow process for a control mass undergoing constant volume, constant pressure, constant temperature, adiabatic and polytropic processes; Free Expansion Process and its examples, its representation on Property diagram; Review of concepts of control volume; Expressions of first law of thermodynamics for a control volume (i.e. open system); Steady State Steady Flow process and its examples; First law analysis of Steady State Flow process e.g. isochoric, isobaric, isothermal, isentropic and polytropic process; Throttling process and its applications; Flow energy or inertial energy of flowing fluids or, Energy transport by mass; Application of Steady State Flow Energy Equation to various engineering devices.\n\n3.Second Law of Thermodynamics:\n\nLimitations of first law of thermodynamics; and how 2nd law is fully able to explain away and thus overcome those shortcomings of Ist law; Thermal Reservoirs, source and sink (Low temperature and high temperatures); Heat Engine, Heat Pump and Refrigerator: definitions, working, efficiency/ performance and their real life examples. Justification as to why the actual efficiency of Heat Pump and Refrigerator shall also be less than equal to 100 percent though on the face of it seems to be more than 100 percent; Various statements of Second Law of Thermodynamics and their equivalence; Philosophy of Carnot cycle and its consequences viz. how each of the individual four processes constituting the cycle contribute in optimizing the output and efficiency of the cycle; Carnot Engine, Carnot Refrigerator and Carnot Heat Pump: definitions, working, efficiency/ performance and Limitations of the cycle; Carnot theorem for heat engines, refrigerators and heat pumps; derivation of Carnot efficiency/COP (which seems to be more than 100 percent); Thermodynamic Temperature Scale; Clausius theorem and Inequality Philosophy and concept of entropy; Entropy changes during various processes; Temperature - Entropy Chart and representation of various processes on it; Principle of Increase of Entropy; Applications of Entropy Principle; Quality of Energy viz. high and low grade energies; Degradation of Energy; Third Law of Thermodynamics.\n\nPART-B\n\n4. Gas Power Cycles:\n\nIntroduction; Concept and philosophy of Air Standard Cycle along with associated assumptions and advantages; Air Standard Efficiency; Nomenclature of reciprocating piston-cylinder arrangement with basic definitions such as swept volume, clearance volume, compression ratio, mean effective pressure etc; Otto Cycle (or constant volume heat addition cycle), Diesel cycle (or constant pressure heat addition cycle) and Dual cycle (Mixed or Composite or Limited Pressure cycle) with their representation on P-V and T-S charts, their Air-standard (thermal) Efficiencies; Comparison of Otto, Diesel and Dual cycle under some defined similar parametric conditions; Introduction to heat engines; Merits of I.C. Engines and their important applications, Classification and construction features of I.C. Engines; working of two stroke and four stroke Petrol and Diesel engines and their comparison.\n\n5. Mechanics of Solids:\n\nIntroduction, Stress, Types of stresses, Hook\'s Law Strain, Longitudinal and lateral strain, Poisson\'s ratio, Stress-strain diagram for ductile and brittle materials, Shear Stress and Shear Strain, Factor of Safety, Principle of Superposition, Strain energy and resilience, Sudden and impact load, Extension of a tapered bar, Extension of a bar due to self-weight, bar of uniform strength, Stress in bars, Thermal Stresses, Elastic constants and their significance, relation between elastic constants, Young\'s modulus of elasticity, Modulus of Rigidity and Bulk modulus.\n\n6. Engineering Materials:\n\nMaterials and Civilization, Materials and Engineering, Classification of Engineering Materials, Significance of various Mechanical Properties of Materials: e.g., elasticity, plasticity, strength, ductility, brittleness, malleability, toughness, resilience, hardness, machinability, formability, weldability. Properties, Composition, and Industrial Applications of materials:metals (ferrous-cast iron, tool steels, stainless steels and non ferrous-Aluminium, brass, bronze), polymers (natural and synthetic , thermoplastic and thermosetting), ceramics (glass, optical fibre glass, cements), Composites(fibre reinforced, metal matrix), Smart materials (piezoelectric, shape memory, thermochromic, photochromic, magnetorheological), Conductors, Semi-conductors and Insulators, Organic and Inorganic materials. Selection of materials for engineering applications.</string>
    <string name="sem2_sub5">PART A (Fundamentals of Computer and IT)\n\n1. Introduction to Computers:\n\nDefine a Computer System, Block diagram of a Computer System and its working, associated peripherals, memories, RAM, ROM, secondary storage devices, Computer Software and Hardware.\n\n2. Working knowledge of Computer System:\n\nIntroduction to the operating system, its functions and types, working knowledge of GUI based operating system, introduction to word processors and its features, creating, editing, printing and saving documents, spell check, mail merge, creating power point presentations, creating spreadsheets and simple graphs, evolution of Internet and its applications and services.\n\n3. Problem Solving and Program Planning:\n\nNeed for problem solving and planning a program; program design tools -algorithms, flow charts, and pseudocode; illustrative examples.\n\nPART B (Basics of Programming Using C++)\n\n4. Overview of C++ Language:\n\nIntroduction to C++ language, structure of a C+ + program, concepts of compiling and linking, IDE and its features; Basic terminology - Character set, tokens, identifiers, keywords, fundamental data types, literal and symbolic constants, declaring variables, initializing variables, type modifiers.5. Operators and expressions Operators in C++, precedence and associativity of operators, expressions and their evaluation, type conversions.\n\n6. Beginning with C++ program:\n\nInput/output using extraction and insertion operators, writing simple C++ programs, comments in C++, stages of program execution.\n\n7. Control Structures:\n\nDecision making statements: if, nested if, if-else.\n\nElse if ladder, switch, Loops and iteration: while loop, for loop, do - while loop, nesting of loops, break statement, continue statement, goto statement, use of control structures through illustrative programming examples.\n\n8. Functions:\n\nAdvantages of using functions, structure of a function, declaring and defining functions, return statement, formal and actual arguments, const argument, default arguments, concept of reference variable, call by value, call by reference, library functions, recursion, storage classes. Use of functions through illustrative programming examples.\n\n9. Arrays and Strings:\n\nDeclaration of arrays, initialization of array, accessing elements of array, I/0 of arrays, passing arrays as arguments to a function, multidimensional arrays. String as array of characters, initializing string variables, I/0 of strings, string manipulation functions (strlen, strcat, strcpy, strcmp), passing strings to a function. Use of arrays and strings through Smys tu a TUNIC LUI. Use vi atiays dnu sumya Iuuyn illustrative programming examples.\n\n10. Concepts of Object Oriented Programming:\n\nIntroduction to Classes, Objects, Data abstraction, Data encapsulation, inheritance and polymorphism.\n\n11.Classes and Objects:\n\nDefining classes and declaring objects, public and private keywords, comstructors and descructors , defining member functions inside and outside of a class , accessing members of a class , friend function. Use of classes and objects through illustrative programming examples.\n\n12.Basics og File Handling:\n\nOpening reading and writing of files , error handling during file operation .</string>
    <string name="sem2_sub6">PART A\n\n1. Ordinary Differential Equations of first order:\n\nExact Differential equations, Equations reducible to exact form by integrating factors; Equations of the first order and higher degree. Clairauts equation. Leibnizs linear and Bernoullis equation.\n\n2. Linear Ordinary Differential Equations of second and higher order:\n\nSolution of linear Ordinary Differential Equations of second and higher order; methods of finding complementary functions and particular integrals.\n\nSpecial methods for finding particular integrals:\n\nMethod of variation of parameters, Operator method.\n\nCauchys homogeneous and Legendres linear equation, Simultaneous linear equations with constant coefficients.\n\n3. Applications of Ordinary Differential Equations Applications to electric R-L-C circuits, Deflection of beams, Simple harmonic motion, Simple population model.\n\nPART B\n\n4. Linear Algebra:\n\nRank of a matrix, Elementary transformation, Linear independence and dependence of vectors, Gauss-Jordan method to find inverse of a matrix, reduction to normal form, Consistency and solution of linear algebraic equations, Linear transformations, Orthogonal transformations, Eigen values, Eigen vectors, Cayley-Hamilton Theorem, Reduction to diagonal form, orthogonal, unitary, Hermitian and similar matrices.\n\n5. Infinite Series:\n\nConvergence and divergence of series, Tests of convergence (without proofs): Comparison test, Integral test, Ratio test, Rabies test, Logarithmic test, Cauchys root test and Gauss test. Convergence and absolute convergence of alternating series.\n\n6. Complex Numbers and elementary functions of complex variable:\n\nDe-Moivres theorem and its applications. Real and Imaginary parts of exponential, logarithmic, circular, inverse circular, hyperbolic, inverse hyperbolic functions of complex variables. Summation of trigonometric series</string>

    <string name="sem2_prac1">1. Analysis of Effluents:\n\nDetermination of water by EDTA method.\nDetermination of H20 by dissolved oxygen analyzer.\nDetermination of turbidity by Nephelometer Determination of Residual Chlorine.\n\n2. Analysis of Fuels and Lubricants\n\nDetermination of Moisture, Volatile and ash content by proximate analysis.\nDetermination of Flash and Fire point by Abee\'s Apparatus Determination of the viscosity.\nDetermination of Acid Value and Aniline point of oil.\nDetermination of refractive index for oils.\n\n3. Instrumental Analysis\n\nDetermination A-max by spectrophotometer and determination of unknown conc of binary mixture of two liquids.\nDetermination of the surface tension by stalagmometer\nDetermination of the concentration of a solution conductometerically.\nDetermination of the strength of a solution pH meterically.\nDistinction between acid, ester, ketone using IR spectrophotometer.\nDetermination of bathochromic shifts, hypsochromic and hyperchromic, hypochromic shift of benzene and its derivatives.\n\n4. Chromatography:\n\nDetermination of Rf value of amino acid by TLC and identification of the amino acid present.\nSeparation of metallic ions by paper chromatography.\nSeparation of ions by using complexing agents Separation of plant pigments, Chlorophyll and carotenoids by column chromatography.\nDetermination of the ion exchange capacity of the given ion exchanger.\nSeparation of ions by ion-exchange method.\n\n5. Synthesis and Green Chemistry experiments\n\nJ. JyuteSS anu VICE CHEMist esperanCE\nPreparation of a polymer phenol/urea formaldehyde resin or hexamethylenediamine adipic acid polymer and determination of carbonyl value or acid value.\nPreparation of aspirin.\nPreparation of ethyl-2-cyano-3-(4"-methoxyphenyl)-propeonate (Microwave assisted reaction).\nBase catalyzed aldol condensation by Green Methodology Acetylation of primary amines using ecofriendly method.\n\nNote: Each student is required to perform two experiments from each of the 5 titles (presented bold)\n\n</string>
    <string name="sem2_prac2">Exercise 1: Study and draw 2-D sketching entities like lines, rectangle, parallelogram polygon, circle etc.,under SKETCH ENTITY MENU.\nExercise 2: (a) Rectangular array (b) Circular array.\nExercise 3: Sketch of Metal grate.\nExercise 4: Slotted Base.\nExercise 5: Link.\nExercise 6: Base Plate (Extruding the sketch).\nExercise 7: Bush (Revolve).\nExercise 8: Handle (Revolve).\nExercise 9: Flange coupling parts.\nExercise 10: Bell Crank Lever.\n\nLab Work-ll: Using the geometric shape and size data learnt in Lab Work I, extrude and revolve the sketch to obtain 3-D drawing. Study and practice various options available for 3-D drawing.\n\nExercise-1: Bracket Lever \nExercise 2: Hand Wheel \nExercise 3: Hexagonal Nut and Bolt \nExercise 4: Keys \nExercise 5: Body of Solid Journal Bearing.\nExercise 6: Shaft.\nExercise 7: Cup of Screw Jack.\nExercise 8: Screw Jack Body.\nExercise 9: V-Block.\nExercise 10: Gland.\n</string>
    <string name="sem2_prac3">1. Familiarization with the Computer System:\n\nTo explain the part of the computer system such as system unit input devices, output devices connected to the computer.\nTo explore the outside view of the system unit that includes the panels on front and ports at the rear.To explore the inside view of the system unit that includes the motherboard processor, expansion slots, various add-on cards, storage devices, power supply, fans.\nTo understand the booting process that includes switching on the system,execution of POST routine, the bootstrap loader, and loading of the operating system, and getting it ready for use.\nTo introduce the graphical user interface (desktop) of Windows operating system To explain the various elements of the desktop such as taskbar, icons (My Computer, Recycle Bin, etc.), short cuts, notification area.\nTo configure the desktop that include selecting the wall paper, selecting the screen saver with or without password protection, selecting the screen resolution and color quality,\n\n2. Navigating with Window Explorer:\n\nTo navigate with the drives \nTo create new folders To move folders from one drive to another drive\n To move files from one folder to another folder\n To search files and folders\n To share files and folders To view and/or change the attributes of the files and folders\n\n3. Working with Control Panel:\n\nTo work with date and time \nTo create new user accounts \nTo install new hardware and configuring existing hardware \nTo install new software or remove existing installed software \nTo configure network connections \nTo manage security profile\n\n4. Miscellaneous Features:\n\nTo work at the command prompt \nTo open an application, folder, document or internet resource from the Run command \nTo initialize storage media (formatting) \nTo understand the menace of viruses \nTo understand the working of virus guards and antivirus software\n\n5. Exploring the Internet:\n\nTo understand the working of the internet that include the use of protocols,domains, IP addresses, URLs, web browsers, web servers, mail-servers, etc.\nTo create email-account, sending mails, receiving mails, sending files as attachments, etc.\nTo login to a remote computer.\nTo search information using search engines\n\n6. Microsoft Word:\n\nTo familiarize with parts of Word window \nTo create and save a document \nTo set page settings, create headers and footers \nTo edit a document and resave it \nTo use copy, cut and paste features\nTo use various formatting features such as bold face, italicize, underline, subscript, superscript, line spacing, etc.\nTo use spelling and grammar checking feature.\nTo preview print a document.\n\n7. Microsoft Word continued:\n\nTo create a table with specified rows and columns \nTo enter data in a table\nTo select a table, a row, a column or a cell \nTo inset new row and/or a column \nTo delete a row and/or a column \nTo split and merge a row, column or a cell \nTo understand the mail-merge and to use mail merge feature of MS-Word\n\n8. Microsoft Excel:\n\nTo familiarize with parts of Excel window \nTo create and save a workbook with single and/or multiple worksheets \nTo edit and format text as well numbers \nTo apply operations on range of cells using built-in formulae\nTo preview and print a worksheet\n\n9. Microsoft Excel continued:\n\nTo insert new row and/or column in a worksheet \nTo delete a row and/or column in a worksheet \nTo create a variety of charts \nTo import and export data to or from worksheet\n\n10. Microsoft PowerPoint:\n\nTo familiarize with parts of PowerPoint window \nTo create and save a new presentation \nTo apply design templates to a presentation \nTo insert, edit and delete a slide \nTo use different views of slides \nTo use slide show from beginning or from the current slide \nTo preview and print a presentation\n\n11. Microsoft PowerPoint continued:\n\nTo check spellings in a presentation \nTo add clip art and pictures in a slide \nTo add chart, diagram and table in a slide \nTo set animation for a selected slide and/or for entire presentation\nTo create slide master and title master \nTo create a custom show\n\n12. Write a program to find the nature of the roots as well as value of the roots. However, in case of imaginary roots, find the real part and imaginary part separately.\n\n13. Write a program, which takes two integer operands and one operator form user, performs the operation and then prints the result. (Consider the operators +,-* !, percentage and use switch statement).For example, the input should be in the form: 5+ 3 the output should comes Result = 8.\n\n14.Fibonacci sequence is defined as follows: the first and second terms in the sequence are 0 and 1.Subsequent terms are found by adding the preceding two terms in the sequence. Write a program to generate the first n terms of the sequence. For example, for n = 8, the output should be 0 11235813.\n\n15.Write a program to print all the prime numbers between m and n, where the value of m and n is supplied by the user.\n\n16. The number such as 1991, is a palindrome because it is same number when read forward or backward.Write a program to check whether the given number is palindrome or not.\n\n17.A positive integer number IJK is said to be well-ordered if I is less than J is less than K. For example, number 138 is called well-ordered because the digits in the number (1, 3, 8) increase from left to right, i.e., 1 is less than 3 is less than 8. Number 365 is not well-ordered because 6 is larger than 5. Write a program that will find and display all possible three digit well-ordered numbers. The program should also display the total number of three digit well-ordered numbers found.\n\n18. Write a function to computer the highest common factor of integer numbers m and n. Use this function to find the highest common factor of integer numbers a and b.\n\n19. Given the marks (out of 100) obtained by each student in a test of a class with n students. Write a program to obtain the following information:\n(a) minimum and maximum marks score.\n(b) average score of the class \n(c) number of students whose score is greater than class average score\n\n20.Write a program to multiply matrix Amxn by Bpxq, given that n = p.\n\n21. Write a program to sort a list of n integer numbers in descending order using bubble sort method.\n\n22. Create a class named Student with the appropriate data members and member functions to generate output comprising student admission no.,name, marks in five subjects and the percentage of marks obtained.Write a program to use the Student class.\n\n23. Create a class named Complex Number with the appropriate data members and constructors. Include member functions (defined inside the class) to perform the following operations:\n(a) Inputting a complex number \n(b) Outputting a complex number \n(c) Arithmetic operations on two complex numbers \nWrite an appropriate program to demonstrate use of the Complex Number class.\n\n24.Create a class named Height with feet and inches as its data members. Also include appropriate constructors (and destructor, if required). Include member functions (defined outside the class) to perform the following operations:\n(a) Inputting a height of a person\n(b) Displaying a height of a person \n(c) To get height in inches \n(d) To compare two heights Write an appropriate program to demonstrate use of the Height class.\n\nNote: Students are required to prepare a file containing lab exercises based on programming only, where as the oral examination will from the entire syllabus</string>
</resources>
